Okay, let's talk about the most
confusing part of agent kit and that's
how OpenAI defines an agent. If you look
at this, it should remind you of
something and that should be this. You
have multiple LLM calls that are chained
together through some sort of
conditional logic gate. And this is what
the industry has started calling
workflows. But now, for some reason,
OpenAI is calling this an agent builder.
And if we go back and look at the new
definition of an agent from OpenAI is an
a AI agent is a system that can do work
independently on behalf of the user.
It's extremely vague and I think it's on
purpose. Here is the definition from
Enthropic. So they say agents are
systems where LLMs dynamically direct
their own processes and tool usage
maintaining control over how they can
accomplish tasks. Now going back to
this, it's actually a welldefined
declarative graph where you as a user or
developer have to define every step that
the agent has to take and then set of
tools that are going to be available but
the whole flow is predefined. Now this
is what enthropic and all of the
industry are calling workflows. So they
are system where LLMs and tools are
orchestrated through predefined code
paths. Now definition matters and if you
read through their blog post it's
extremely confusing. So for example
they're saying design workflows with
agent builder. Now here's the kicker. A
few months ago openai released this a
practical guide to building agents. Now
in this they had this to say about
declarative and non-declarative graphs.
So they said some frameworks are
declarative at this point they were most
probably pointing towards lang graph.
Now in here say requiring developers to
explicitly define every branch loop and
conditional in the workflow upfront
through graphs consisting of nodes which
are agents and edges deterministic or
dynamic handoff. While beneficial for
visual clarity, this approach can
quickly become cumbersome and
challenging as workflows grow more
dynamic and complex, often necessitating
the learning of specialized domain
specific languages. Now, if you look at
this, this is exactly what OpenAI is
trying to do with their new agent
builder. Now don't get me wrong, it has
a lot of useful cases and I actually
personally really like their
implementation
but I also agree with what they are
saying in here. Now then they go on to
say in contrast the agent SDK adopts a
more flexible code first approach.
Developers can directly express workflow
logic using familiar programming
constructs without needing to predefine
the entire graph of print enabling more
dynamic and adoptable agent
orchestration. So with this you can
actually go and generate code and is
using the agent SDK in the back end. But
again you are defining workflows not
building agents. And at this point it it
is probably helpful to understand what
exactly a workflow is. So if you if you
look at your current workflow in terms
of how you solve problem, you could
potentially translate that into a
declarative decision graph and express
those actions with the help of an LLM
such as like this. The LLM can take
decision at different points based on
the available tools. But you as a user
define what those actions and conditions
are going to look like. And in my humble
opinion, in most business applications,
that's exactly what you want to do.
There are different types of workflows
that you can put together. And if you
read through Enthropics blog post, they
have six or seven different
configurations where they explain how
these workflows can uh be put together
to solve specific problems.
Now agents on the other hand have the
ability to plan, take actions and modify
their plan based on the feedback that
they get from the environment or the
results of those actions. So here's a
quick example of what those actions and
the results could look like. So let's
say you have a number of different tools
that are available to the model. Sele
the model can select a specific tool
based on its needs that is going to go
to the context of the model. Then the
model takes action. The tool call
generates the results that goes to the
history of the model and then based on
those observations the LLM can update
its plan and take more actions. So there
is a lot more flexibility in autonomous
agents and we have seen very interesting
response to OpenAI's workflow builder or
agent builder. So here's a very
interesting blog post from Harrison
Chase who is the CEO of Langchain and I
think it in this he highlights a few
issues with visual workflow builders. So
first of all they are not low barrier to
entry. So here argue that despite being
built for mass audience, it is still not
easy for average non-technical user to
use them. Which kind of goes back to the
point that OpenAI was making a few
months ago. And the second point that he
highlights is complex tasks quickly
become too complicated to manage in
visual builder which again is a valid
criticism of visual builders. Now in
here he is making a case for langraph
right. So take it with a grain of salt
but time will tell. One thing which I
also want to highlight is that some
people think that agent builder will
probably kill a number of different
visual builders which I don't think is
the case. Specifically, people talk
about tools like Zapier, Make Natn,
right? But if you look at some of the
MCPs, they actually have support for
Zapier, which makes it extremely
powerful because it enables the
connectors or integrations Zapier has
that you can actually bring into
OpenAI's agent builder or agent kit.
Now, since everything is through an MCP,
you can theoretically bring in a lot
more than the current list that they
have, but time will tell how effective
this new agent kit is going to be. I
personally think that although it is
advertised to developers, probably it's
not specifically for developers,
developers probably want a lot more
control than a visual builder.
Now, time will tell because they also
have pretty neat features in terms of
you can build evals and the integration
seems to be pretty smooth. However, keep
in mind if you're using OpenAI agent
kit, it has very strong vendor lock in
and that means since it's an OpenAI
product, you are limited to OpenAI
models.
But since it has support for MCPS, you
can theoretically bring in other models.
Although they were not going to be
driving the overall flow or structure.
But I think since it's built on top of
agents SDK, there might be a way around
it that you build a workflow here, test
it, and then potentially replace the
models with other models. We'll have to
test whether that is going to work or
not. Anyways, do let me know what you
think about agent kit and agents in
general. How do you see the difference
between workflows and autonomous agents?
Let me know your thoughts in the comment
section below. Anyways, I hope you found
this video useful. Thanks for watching
and as always, see you in the next one.